<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<webpage menu="main">
   <title>EXPath - Modules</title>
   <section>
      <title>Modules</title>
      <para> Most of the extensions will be of the form of function libraries. Each module is an
         independent, consistent piece of the whole project, addressing a particular issue or
         feature area. </para>
   </section>
   <divider/>
   <primary>
      <title>Packaging System</title>
      <details>Packaging and delivering all your X* stuff</details>
      <para>A standard packaging system for several core XML technologies, like XSLT, XQuery, XProc
         and XML Schema. Once packaged, libraries can be deployed on every supporting processor. See
         the <link href="modules/pkg/">packaging page</link>.</para>
   </primary>
   <primary>
      <title>XProject</title>
      <details>A tool to automate usual tasks on an XML project</details>
      <para>While working on an XML project, one has typically to repeat the same tasks over and
         over again. Like building a package with the current state of the sources, generating
         documentation or unit-testing the several components. XProject automates all those (boring)
         tasks and let you focus directly on your code, instead of having to set up your environment
         or writing the same scripts over and over again. See the <link href="modules/xproject/"
            >XProject page</link>.</para>
   </primary>
   <primary>
      <title>Webapp Container</title>
      <details>Writing web applications in X*, from cover to cover</details>
      <para>A standard web application container and framework, for several core XML technologies,
         like XSLT, XQuery and XProc.  See the <link href="modules/webapp/">webapps
         page</link>.</para>
   </primary>
   <primary>
      <title>File Handling</title>
      <details>Files and directories details and modifications</details>
      <para>This module defines a set of functions to read the file system informations, and to
         modify it.  In other words, it allows you to read files, list directories, create them,
         and get several informations about files.  See the <link href="modules/file/">module
         page</link> for details.</para>
   </primary>
   <primary>
      <title>Geospatial API</title>
      <details>The Open Geospatial Consortium Simple Features Common Access API for XPath</details>
      <para>The EXPath Geo module defines functions that may be applied to well-formed valid
         geometries conforming to the Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) Simple Feature (SF) data
         model.  Typically, such features will be encoded as Geography Markup Language
         geometries.  Other encodings, for example KML, may also be supported by an
         implementation.  See the <link href="modules/geo/">module page</link> for details.</para>
   </primary>
   <primary>
      <title>HTTP Client</title>
      <details>Sending HTTP requests, and receiving the responses</details>
      <para>This module defines a set of functions to send HTTP requests and handle responses. This
         is a quite low-level functionality, allowing one to deal with most aspects of the HTTP
         protocol, while integrating smoothly within the <link
            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath-datamodel/">XPath Data Model</link>. See the <link
            href="modules/http-client/">module page</link> for details.</para>
   </primary>
   <primary>
      <title>ZIP Facility</title>
      <details>Reading and writing ZIP files</details>
      <para>This module provides a set of functions to read the structure of a ZIP file, read
         entries out of a ZIP file, update entries in an existing ZIP file or create brand-new
         files. So it will provide the ability to deal with Microsoft’s <link
            href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_Open_XML">Open XML</link>, OASIS’s <link
            href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenDocument">OpenDocument</link>, other
         ZIP-and-XML-based document formats, like <link href="http://www.openebook.org/">EPUB</link>
         eBooks, or simply any plain ZIP file. See the <link href="modules/zip/">module page</link>
         for details.</para>
   </primary>
</webpage>
