<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<webpage menu="faq">
   <title>EXPath - FAQ</title>
   <section>
      <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
      <!--image src="images/machine.jpg" alt="Machine"/-->
      <para>This page gathers informations about the project in a whole, and answers most frequently
         asked questions. It will evolve with time, so be sure to check it from time to time.</para>
      <list>
         <item>
            <link hre="#licence">What's the licencing?</link>
         </item>
         <item>
            <link hre="#version">Versioning policy</link>
         </item>
         <item>
            <link hre="#scope">What's the exact scope of EXPath?</link>
         </item>
      </list>
   </section>
   <divider/>
   <primary id="licence">
      <title>What's the licencing?</title>
      <para>The website content is under the <link
            href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">Creative Commons 2.5</link>. The
         specifications are under the <link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/"
            >Creative Commons 3.0 No Derivative</link>.</para>
      <para>Each implementation has to provide clear licencing information. They are encouraged to
         use the <link href="http://www.mozilla.org/MPL/">Mozilla Public License</link>, but other
         open source licences could be accepted if the context requires to. Please check the
         delivery notes of the implementations you want to use.</para>
   </primary>
   <primary id="version">
      <title>Versioning policy</title>
      <para>Each module specification is developed collaboratively by the community, under the lead
         of one (or a few) editor. Working drafts are publicized to get feedback from the community
         and to allow implementation of the current state of affairs. But only the accepted modules
         should be used for production works; their versioning scheme is a major and a minor
         numbers, dot-separated (1.0, 1.1, etc.)</para>
      <para>The namespace URIs used by the specifications are of the form
            <code>http://expath.org/ns/[module-name]</code> and should not include any versioning
         information (unless it was properly justified.) The same namespace URI should be used for
         the whole module; in particular, error codes should not be defined in anther namespace than
         functions or elements used as return values or parameters.</para>
   </primary>
   <primary id="scope">
      <title>What's the exact scope of EXPath?</title>
      <para>The goal of this project is to provide the community with organized sets of extensions
         to the XPath 2.0 language. TODO: ... can be done in plenty of ways ... privilege functions
         and ban grammar changes ... if another lib exists, maybe just link to it ... don't want to
         restrict too much, and trust good sense of the community; if people spend time to define
         and implement module then why not? ... XSLT and XQuery should not have a particular
         position in this project, but because their thigh relations with each other, the border is
         not always obvious. The privileged mean of extension is clearly the function: defining
      </para>
   </primary>
</webpage>
