<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<webpage menu="main">
   <title>EXPath - FAQ</title>
   <section>
      <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
      <image src="images/machine.jpg" alt="Machine"/>
      <para>This page gathers informations about the project in a whole, and answers most frequently
         asked questions. It will evolve over time, so be sure to check it from time to time.</para>
      <list>
         <item>
            <link href="#who">How does decide what to define in EXPath?</link>
         </item>
         <item>
            <link href="#licence">What's the licencing?</link>
         </item>
         <item>
            <link href="#version">Versioning policy</link>
         </item>
         <item>
            <link href="#scope">What's the exact scope of EXPath?</link>
         </item>
         <item>
            <link href="#xpath21">Is not there a risk to be redundant with XPath 2.1?</link>
         </item>
      </list>
      <para/>
      <para>The <link href="resources">resources</link> page contains also useful links and
         documentation, as well as the <link href="wiki/">EXPath wiki</link>.</para>
   </section>
   <divider/>
   <primary id="licence">
      <title>What's the licencing?</title>
      <para>The website content is under the <link
            href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">Creative Commons 2.5</link>. The
         specifications are under the <link href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/"
            >Creative Commons 3.0 No Derivative</link>.</para>
      <para>Each implementation has to provide clear licencing information. They are encouraged to
         use the <link href="http://www.mozilla.org/MPL/">Mozilla Public License</link>, but other
         open source licences could be accepted if the context requires to. Please check the
         delivery notes of the implementations you want to use.</para>
   </primary>
   <primary id="version">
      <title>Versioning policy</title>
      <para>Each module specification is developed collaboratively by the community, under the lead
         of one (or a few) editor. Working drafts are publicized to get feedback from the community
         and to allow implementation of the current state of affairs. But only the accepted modules
         should be used for production works; their versioning scheme is a major and a minor
         numbers, dot-separated (1.0, 1.1, etc.)</para>
      <para>The namespace URIs used by the specifications are of the form
            <code>http://expath.org/ns/[module-name]</code> and should not include any versioning
         information (unless it was properly justified.) The same namespace URI should be used for
         the whole module; in particular, error codes should not be defined in anther namespace than
         functions or elements used as return values or parameters.</para>
   </primary>
   <primary id="scope">
      <title>What's the exact scope of EXPath?</title>
      <para>The goal of this project is to provide the community with organized sets of extensions
         to the XPath 2.0 language. That can be done in plenty of different ways, but here we
         clearly favor defining extension through functions, and forbid grammar-level changes. If
         another library does exist yet that address one problem, we should maybe link to it and not
         try to reinvent the wheel.</para>
      <para>But I don't want to restrict too much the freedom of the module maintainers nor their
         creativity, and I trust the good sense of the community. If people spend time to define and
         implement a module, even if they not respect the above rules, and if there is some interest
         in the community regarding this work, then why not?</para>
      <para>XSLT and XQuery should not have any particular position in this project, but because
         their tight relationships with each other, the border is not always obvious.</para>
   </primary>
   <primary id="xpath21">
      <title>Is not there a risk to be redundant with XPath 2.1?</title>
      <para>Yes, there is a risk. Actually, there is a risk to define something that will be in
         XPath 2.1, and there is the risk to rely on something that will change in the different
         drafts. But the risk can be reduced by asking the Working Group if something similar is on
         its way to the XPath 2.1 Working Draft, and even if it is the case, that could be
         interesting to have a parallel work to give feedback to the WG.</para>
      <para>So the risk does exist, and we have to keep this future draft in mind. But this is
         absolutely not a reason to not work on EXPath for now. This is the responsibility of each
         editor to evaluate the situation and see if he wants to take the risk or not, and if he is
         ready to follow closely the evolution of XPath 2.1.</para>
   </primary>
   <secondary id="who" box="true">
      <title>How does decide what to define in EXPath?</title>
      <para>You do!</para>
      <para>EXPath is a collaborative, community-driven project. If you need a module which does not
         exist in EXPath, but you think would be worth having as an EXPath module, you can propose
         it on the <link href="lists">mailing list</link>.</para>
      <para>But do not expect to find someone telling you that this is the best idea he never heard,
         and who is ready to invest all his spare time in defining and implementing what you want.
         The best option is to first discuss it on the list, to be sure no one else is working on a
         similar feature, or that such a feature does not exist somewhere else. And maybe get some
         advice of people who have thought about the same ideas. Then write a formal specification:
         the function prototypes, their behavior, the context, etc. This will be concrete material
         to discuss and to propose to be reviewed by pairs.</para>
      <para>Discussing a module that no one is ready to actually spend time on it is just loosing
         time. So launch your preferred editor and start writing down your ideas!</para>
   </secondary>
</webpage>
