<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="webpage.xsl"?-->

<webpage menu="implems" root="../..">
   <title>EXPath - HTTP Client Implementations</title>
   <section>
      <title>HTTP Client Implementations</title>
      <image src="../../images/web2.jpg" alt="Spider web"/>
      <para>For now, there are three implementations: for <link href="http://www.saxonica.com/"
            >Saxon</link> (XSLT 2.0 and XQuery,) for <link href="http://www.exist-db.org/"
            >eXist</link>, and for <link href="http://www.marklogic.com/">MarkLogic Server</link>.
         The later two are partial implementations though, as they rely on the similar,
         product-dependent extension of these products, which do not permit to provide the whole
         functionality. Anyone is welcome to contribute of course, see the <link
            href="../../lists.html">mailing list</link>. I plan to provide a better support on these
         platform later.</para>
      <para>For Saxon, you have the XAR package: <link href="expath-http-client-saxon-0.4.xar"
            >expath-http-client-saxon-0.4.xar</link>. This package follows the EXPath <link
            href="../pkg/">Packaging System</link> format and can be installed with the package
         manager. See the packaging system implementations page for more information.</para>
      <para>For eXist, you can download the following X* archive: <link
            href="expath-http-client-exist-0.1.xar">expath-http-client-exist-0.1.xar</link>. This is
         a package for the EXPath <link href="../pkg/">Packaging System</link>. You can use the
         package manager for eXist, or just open it as a ZIP file and use the
            <code>http-client.xq</code> file it contains. Since the version 1.4 (and the last 1.3.*
         dev versions) it is included in the standard distribution, so you don't even have to
         install it!</para>
      <para>For MarkLogic Server, you can download the following tarball: <link
            href="expath-http-client-marklogic-0.1.tar.gz"
            >expath-http-client-marklogic-0.1.tar.gz</link> or the equivalent ZIP file: <link
            href="expath-http-client-marklogic-0.1.zip">expath-http-client-marklogic-0.1.zip</link>.
         See instructions within there about how to install the library module on your MarkLogic
         instance, and how to import it in your query.</para>
      <para>Request for help: this is the very first module for EXPath. If you have any thought,
         idea, comment or advice on how modules should be delivered, installed, deployed, used,
         packaged..., please comment on the <link href="../../lists.html">mailing
         list</link>.</para>
   </section>
</webpage>
