<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<webpage menu="hc" root="../..">
   <title>EXPath - HTTP Client</title>
   <section>
      <title>HTTP Client</title>
      <image src="../../images/web1.jpg" alt="Machine"/>
      <para>This module defines a set of functions to send HTTP &amp; HTTPS requests and handle
         responses. This is a quite low-level functionality, allowing one to deal with most aspects
         of the HTTP protocol (redirections, headers, body contents, multipart...), while
         integrating smoothly within the <link href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath-datamodel/">XPath
            Data Model</link>.</para>
      <para>This module was written initially for EXSLT 2.0, but it is really an XPath extension,
         that makes sense to be used in XQuery as well, for instance. It is being moved to EXPath,
         but the <link href="http://www.fgeorges.org/exslt2/">legacy page</link> is still available.
         As this is the first EXPath module so far, any thought about how it should be released and
         about packaging would be much appreciated on the <link href="../../lists.html">mailing
            list</link>.</para>
   </section>
   <divider/>
   <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>Besides the <link href="../http-client.html">specification</link>, here is an informal
         introduction to this module. See also the <link href="samples.html">samples page</link> for
         more elaborate samples. This module defines a single function,
            <code>http:send-request()</code> (with several arities for the sake of ease of use.) The
         function takes a description of the request in parameter, and returns a representation of
         the response.</para>
      <para>The request is represented by an <code>http:request</code> element, giving the URI, the
         HTTP method, the headers and the body content (for POST and PUT methods.) The response is
         returned as a sequence of one or more items. The first one is an <code>http:response</code>
         element with quite the same structure as an <code>http:request</code>, but without the
         content itself. The content is returned as the second item (or several items in case of a
         multipart response) as a string, a document node or a binary item, depending on the
            <code>Content-Type</code> returned by the server. Here is a simple example of call in
         XQuery, which sends a text content by POST:</para>
      <para>
         <sample href="index-1.xq.sample" kind="xquery"/>
      </para>
      <para>The response element can look like the following:</para>
      <para>
         <sample href="index-2.xml.sample" kind="xml"/>
      </para>
      <para>It is important to understand that the result of the function, in the example of the
         above call, is a sequence of 2 items: the <code>http:response</code> element, and a
         document node representing the HTML document. Here is an example of query that illustrate
         that fact; it checks the status of the response within the <code>http:response</code>
         element, then use the title element in the HTML document:</para>
      <para>
         <sample href="index-3.xsl.sample" kind="xml"/>
      </para>
      <para>You can find other examples on the <link href="samples.html">samples page</link>.</para>
   </section>
   <!--secondary>
      <title>Links</title>
      <para>The specification for this module can be found <link href="../http-client.html"
         >here</link>.</para>
      <para>Implementations of this module for various XSLT and XQuery processors can be found <link
            href="implems.html">here</link>.</para>
      <para>Samples of use of this module in both XSLT and XQuery can be found <link
            href="samples.html">here</link>.</para>
   </secondary-->
</webpage>
