<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<webpage menu="pkg" root="../..">
   <title>EXPath - Package Managers</title>
   <section>
      <title>Package Managers</title>
      <image src="../../images/packaging.jpg" alt="Taps and pipes"/>
      <para>The Packaging System specification is still under development, but three implementations
         have been released yet, supporting the current state of the working draft. Those
         implementations are for the <link href="http://www.exist-db.org/">eXist</link> database,
         for the <link href="http://www.saxonica.com/">Saxon</link> XSLT and XQuery processor and
         for the <link href="http://xmlcalabash.com/">Calabash</link> XProc processor. Those
         implementations are just prototypes that add packaging support to those processors, as
         external libraries. In addition, there is a standalone application to manage a repository
         on the disk (Saxon and Calabash use the same repository layout, while eXist uses its own
         method to deploy packages, based on JAR files.) Keep in mind that this module, and its
         implementations, can evolve (and will do) in the near future, depending on the feedback got
         from the community.</para>
      <para>The current packaging <link href="../../spec/pkg">specification</link> defines a
            <bold>standard repository</bold> layout. Currently, this layout is supported by
         implementations for both Saxon and Calabash. The repository manager is thus common. It is a
         command line program that allows one to initialize a new repository, install packages,
         delete packages, list the installed packages, etc. Download the JAR file <link
            href="expath-pkg-repo-0.1.jar">expath-pkg-repo-0.1.jar</link>, and use the command
            <code>java -jar expath-pkg-repo-0.1.jar</code>. For more information, see this <link
            href="http://fgeorges.blogspot.com/2009/11/expath-packaging-system-on-disk.html">blog
            post</link>. In addition to this repository manager, you need a runtime support for your
         processor (for now, Saxon and Calabash support the standard repository layout, eXist has
         its own way of deploying packages.)</para>
      <para>The runtime support for <bold>Saxon</bold> is included in the JAR file <link
            href="expath-pkg-saxon-0.2.jar">expath-pkg-saxon-0.2.jar</link>. In addition, the
         classpath must contain the JAR file for the repository management (see above.) If you use
         Saxon from Java, you can use the class <code>org.expath.pkg.saxon.java.ConfigHelper</code>.
         If you use Saxon from the command line, you have to use
            <code>org.expath.pkg.saxon.java.EXPathTransform</code> as the main class for XSLT 2.0,
         or <code>org.expath.pkg.saxon.java.EXPathQuery</code> for XQuery, instead of the Saxon's
         main classes (resp. <code>net.sf.saxon.Transform</code> and
         <code>net.sf.saxon.Query</code>.) You can use the following shell script to help you
         setting up the classpath with the extensions installed in the repository and written in
         Java: <link href="expath-pkg-saxon-0.2.sh">expath-pkg-saxon-0.2.sh</link>. See this <link
            href="http://fgeorges.blogspot.com/2009/10/expath-packaging-system-prototype.html">blog
            post</link> and this <link
            href="http://fgeorges.blogspot.com/2009/11/expath-packaging-system-on-disk.html">blog
            post</link> for more information (the first one is older and about Saxon in porticular,
         the second one is up-to-date and more specifically about the shell script.)</para>
      <para>For Calabash you can use the same instructions as for Saxon above, by adding in addition
         the following JAR file to your classpath: <link href="expath-pkg-calabash-0.1.jar"
            >expath-pkg-calabash-0.1.jar</link>, by using <code>org.expath.pkg.calabash.Main</code>
         and the following shell script: <link href="expath-pkg-calabash-0.1.sh"
            >expath-pkg-calabash-0.1.sh</link>. See this <link
            href="http://fgeorges.blogspot.com/2009/11/expath-packaging-system-on-disk.html">blog
            post</link> and this <link
            href="http://fgeorges.blogspot.com/2009/11/expath-packaging-system-prototype.html">blog
            post</link> for more information.</para>
      <para>The package manager for <bold>eXist</bold> is provided as a single <link
            href="expath-pkg-exist-0.1.jar">JAR file</link>. Just download it and launch it the
         usual way (depending on your platform, that could be by double-clicking on it, or by
         executing the command <code>java -jar expath-pkg-exist-0.1.jar</code>.) For now, it
         requires a windowing system, but a text oriented interface will be provided later, to
         enable its usage on graphical-less environments, like servers. You can find a step-by-step
         presentation of this package manager in the following <link
            href="http://fgeorges.blogspot.com/2009/09/expath-packaging-system-prototype.html">blog
            post</link>.</para>
   </section>
</webpage>
