<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<webpage menu="implems" root="../..">
   <title>EXPath - Package Managers</title>
   <section>
      <title>Package Managers</title>
      <image src="../../images/packaging.jpg" alt="Taps and pipes"/>
      <para>The Packaging System specification is still under development, but three implementations
         have been released yet, supporting the current state of the working draft. Those
         implementations are for the <link href="http://www.exist-db.org/">eXist database</link> ,
         for the <link href="http://www.saxonica.com/">Saxon XSLT and XQuery processor</link> et for
         the <link href="http://xmlcalabash.com/">Calabash XProc processor</link>. Those
         implementations are just prototypes that add packaging support to those processors, as
         external libraries. In addition, there is a standalone application to manage a repository
         on the disk (Saxon and Calabash use the same repository layout, while eXist uses its own
         method to deploy packages, based on JAR files.) Keep in mind that this module, and its
         implementations, can evolve (and will do) in the near future, depending on the feedback got
         from the community.</para>
      <para>The package manager for eXist is provided as a single <link
            href="expath-pkg-exist-0.1.jar">JAR file</link>. Just download it and launch it the
         usual way (depending on your platform, that could be by double-clicking on it, or by
         executing the command <code>java -jar expath-pkg-exist-0.1.jar</code>.) For now, it
         requires a windowing system, but a text oriented interface will be provided later, to
         enable its usage on graphical-less environments, like servers. You can find a step-by-step
         presentation of this package manager in the following <link
            href="http://fgeorges.blogspot.com/2009/09/expath-packaging-system-prototype.html">blog
            post</link>.</para>
      <para>The package manager for Saxon is provided as a single <link
            href="expath-pkg-saxon-0.1.jar">JAR file</link>. If you launch it (either by
         double-clicking on it, or by executing the command <code>java -jar
            expath-pkg-saxon-0.1.jar</code>) the package manager itself starts. This is the
         graphical application which allows you to install and remove packages, and manage
         repositories. This JAR file also contains classes needed at runtime by Saxon to resolve the
         stuff installed in the repository. If you want to call Saxon from a shell window, you can
         use the following <link href="expath-pkg-saxon-0.1.sh">shell script</link> to set up
         correctly your classpath. You can find a step-by-step presentation of this package manager
         in the following <link
            href="http://fgeorges.blogspot.com/2009/10/expath-packaging-system-prototype.html">blog
            post</link>.</para>
   </section>
</webpage>
