<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../webpage.xsl"?-->

<webpage menu="pkg" root="../..">
   <title>EXPath - Packaging System</title>
   <section>
      <title>Packaging System</title>
      <image src="../../images/packaging.jpg" alt="Taps and pipes"/>
      <para>Unlike most the other modules, the Packaging System module does not define a set of
         XPath functions, but rather a file format to package libraries written in some core XML
         technologies. The goal is to support XSLT, XQuery and XProc in a first time, but support
         for other related technologies could be added in the future (like XML Schema, XForms, etc.)
         It also supports packaging of extension functions written in a processor-specific way (for
         instance in Java,) for mainstream processors. it is also extensible by third parties, for
         instance to support processor-dependent features.</para>
   </section>
   <divider/>
   <primary>
      <title>Prototype for Saxon and eXist</title>
      <para>The ideal situation would be to have support for this packaging system right into the
         various processors, tools and IDEs. Vendors will follow if there are enough users of this
         system, and users will follow if there is enough support into their tools. So to break that
         circle, we have to provide an implementation for various processors, even a partial
         implementation. Doing so, we can get feedback from the community while defining the module,
         the idea being the module will be easier to explain and that will ease discussions (by
         having something concrete to discuss about...)</para>
      <para>So you can find here a prototype implementation for Saxon, and another one for eXist.
         They are not production-ready, but they should be stable enough to help you installing and
         managing the libraries using the Packaging System (all the EXPath module implementations,
         of course, but we plan also to help writers of major XSLT and XQuery libraries to package
         their work, for instance the stylesheets for DocBook, XSLStyle, FunctX for both XSLT and
         XQuery, the stylesheets for DITA, the FXSL library, etc.)</para>
      <para>See the <link href="implems">implementations page</link> for further
         details.</para>
   </primary>
   <secondary box="true">
      <para>
         <emph>If a technology is too complicated, no matter how wonderful it is and how easy it
            makes a user’s life, it won’t be adopted on a wide scale.</emph>
      </para>
      <para>
         <emph>-- <link href="http://www.ddj.com/184404686">James Clark</link></emph>
      </para>
   </secondary>
</webpage>
